Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is ק"ט, Kuf Tes,
בבא קמא Bava Kamma 109, we're at the משנה Mishna at the
bottom of ק"ח עמוד ב', Kuf Ches Amud Bais, and we're in
the middle of a discussion about the section in the תורה Torah
where it speaks about somebody swearing falsely about stealing an object and
that he has to return when he comes and admits it, he
has to return the object and add a fifth, and also bring
a קרבן אשם. Korban Asham. So let's take a look at the
משנה. Mishna. היכן פקדוני, Heichan pikdoni, bottom of ק"ח עמוד ב': Kuf
Ches Amud Bais: where is my the object that I entrusted you
with? אמר לו אבד: Amar lo avad: it lost, it got lost,
and he was a שומר חנם, Shomer chinam, so he's claiming that
it was lost and he's exempt. משביעך אני: Mashpi'acha ani: he says
I force you to take an oath that that's what happened. ואמר
אמן: Va'amar amein: and the שומר Shomer said, he said yes, I
swear, you know, that it got
lost. ועדים העידוהו שאכלו: V'eideim i'iduhu she'achalo: so there's a case again
of stealing something, swearing falsely about it, in his very act of
swearing he was stealing it, and now we find out that actually
he consumed it and he took it. משלם קרן: Mishaleim keren: so
then he only pays the principal even though he swore falsely. The
special פרשה Parsha in the תורה Torah is only when he admits
on his own. הודה מעצמו, Hodeh mei'atzmo, however, if he admits on
his own and not the עדים Eideim testified, then משלם קרן, mishaleim
keren, not only does he pay the principal, but וחומש, v'chomesh, he
adds a fifth, ואשם, v'asham, and he brings a קרבן אשם. Korban
Asham. So in a way it's a bigger punishment, but ultimately it's
not a punishment, this is what brings him atonement. Now, היכן פקדוני.
Heichan pikdoni. Now let's say he said where the the person who
entrusted the object said, where's the object I entrusted you?
אמר לו נגנב: Amar lo nignav: it was stolen, another way of
getting out of it. משביעך אני: Mashpi'acha ani: I swear you I,
you know, I impose an oath on you. ואמר אמן: Va'amar amein:
and he said אמן amein and he answered אמן amein to the
oath. ועדים העידוהו שגנבו: V'eideim i'iduhu shegnavao: and where and the witnesses
testify that he actually has kept it to himself. שגנבו Shegnavao here
just meaning he himself kept it when he claimed it was lost
or stolen, when he claimed it was נגנב. nignav. So משלם תשלומי
כפל. mishaleim tashlumei kheifel. In that case, as contrasted to the first
one where he said it was lost, here he says it was
burgled, it was נגנב, nignav, so the הלכה halacha is that טוען
טענת גנב, to'ein ta'anas gannav, that if somebody says it was נגנב,
nignav, then he himself is treated like the גנב gannav and he
there will pay כפל kheifel just like a גנב gannav will pay
כפל. kheifel. Okay, so the big difference between when he says אבד
avad he pays only the principal, when he says נגנב nignav and
the witnesses come he pays כפל. kheifel. However, הודה מעצמו, hodeh mei'atzmo,
here he'll it'll be less. If he admits on his own, then
that does not that's not the category of גניבה gineiva and כפל
kheifel which requires עדים, eideim, but it's the category of this פרשה
parsha of the שבועה. shvu'ah. Then משלם קרן וחומש ואשם. mishaleim keren
v'chomesh v'asham. He pays the principal and a fifth and the אשם.
asham. Okay, that's the first part of the משנה mishna and the
גמרא Gemara is not going to discuss that, it's pretty straightforward. Let's
look at the next part of the משנה mishna which will be
the focus of the גמרא. Gemara. הגוזל את אביו: Hagozeil es aviv:
somebody steals from his father. ונשבע לו ומת: V'nishba lo u'meis: and
he swears to his father falsely, he says I didn't steal it,
and then the father died. So now the complicating factor is that
he inherits his father. So he has to return the object, who
is he going to return it to? So let's take a look.
הרי זה משלם קרן וחומש ואשם, Hareizeh mishaleim keren v'chomesh v'asham, or
he pays the principal and the fifth, ואשם v'asham is like in
parentheses here because the focus is who is he paying it to,
who is he paying the principal and the fifth? לבניו או לאחיו:
L'banav o l'achiv: to his sons or his brothers. Now there's a
whole big debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot and רמב"ם Rambam
how to read this. I'm going to read this first like רמב"ם.
Rambam. Okay, רמב"ם Rambam says that he pay he gives it to
and רמב"ם's Rambam גרסא girsa is actually verse, לאחיו או לבניו. l'achiv
o l'banav. First he pays he gives it to his brothers even
though in a way he was an equal inherited the father, and
if there are three brothers maybe a third of what he stole
really what he would have inherited had he not stolen it, it
doesn't matter. He has a מצוה mitzvah to return the object he
stole, he has to get it out of his possession or the
value of it, and he would go ahead and he would give
it to his brothers who also who now represent the father. Or,
if he doesn't have brothers, the רמב"ם Rambam had the גרסא girsa
first לאחיו, l'achiv, then he could give it to his son because
his son would have inherited from him, you know, so his son
to some degree as the grandson of the person who died represents
the person who died. But the key is he's got to get
it out of his possession. Even if he is the sole heir
and he like he would have inherited it all from his father,
it doesn't matter. He stole it, he swore, there's a מצוה mitzvah
to get it out of your possession and he would give it
to his son. Now, אם אינו רוצה או שאין לו: im eino
rotzeh o she'ein lo: now if he doesn't want to, meaning, you
know, he he's very poor and he can't afford giving up this
object, or אין לו ein lo which for רמב"ם Rambam would mean
that he doesn't have any brothers and he doesn't have a son.
So what's he going to do? He's the sole heir, there's nobody
that represents the father. How is he going to get it out
of his possession? So what will he do? לווה ובעל חוב בא
ונפרע. loveh ubaal chov ba venifra.
So he borrows money and when it is time to pay the
debt, this is the way רמב"ם Rambam reads it, when it's time
to pay the debt,
he would just pay the debt.
He would pay the debt with this thing that he stole, okay?
Or with the so and we'll see in the גמרא Gemara he'll
sort of say this is the object I stole from my father.
But because he's giving it to someone, even though that someone are
creditors that he owes money to, that has to be some type
of a ritual returning of the object. He needs to get the
object out of his possession. Or if it's money, he needs to
get the money that represents the object, if the object is destroyed,
out of his possession. That's the way רמב"ם Rambam reads it. רש"י
Rashi reads it a little different, רש"י Rashi or not a little,
a lot different. רש"י Rashi reads it that this is all about
him being able to hold on to the portion he would have
inherited. So if there's two brothers, let's ignore the issue of בכור,
bechor, and he had never stolen from his father, he would have
been able to keep a third of this object. And therefore רש"י
Rashi says if he doesn't, he gives it to his father's sons,
his brothers, who would have inherited, or his father's brothers, he gives
it to somebody that because if his father doesn't have any sons,
then his brothers inherit from him. Those are the people he gives
it to. But if he doesn't want to or he doesn't have
any money, meaning he can't afford losing this third that would have
been coming to him. So then what he does is he borrows
money and he uses the money to pay
his brothers or his uncles, and when they pay them the value
of the object, let's say the object was worth a thousand dollars,
or let's say nine hundred to make it divisible by three. He
borrows nine hundred dollars, he gives it to the brothers, and then
when the creditors come and ask him for his nine hundred dollars
back, he basically points them to three hundred of the dollars he'll
collect from the brothers and he'll pay the other six. So somehow
that way, it's not exactly clear how that works, but somehow in
that way he's able to not have to lose he gave the
full nine hundred dollars back, but eventually he doesn't lose the full,
he only loses the two-thirds that would not have been coming to
him, not the third that would have been coming to him. That's
the way רש"י Rashi reads it. It's not exactly clear how that
works. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot has a different take. תוספות Tosafot has yet
a third read of this. תוספות Tosafot says is that he borrows,
let's that basically he can't give up any of it. So what's
he going to do? He is going to borrow,
let's say it's worth a thousand dollars, he'll borrow a thousand dollars
and he'll say to the creditors this object I stole is going
to be the collateral for the loan. Then he gives the object
to the brothers, and then the creditors come and they have a
lien on that object, and they come and they take it from
the brothers. And that way he does not lose any money, he
keeps his thousand dollars and the object gets taken from the brother.
Or if it's land and if the object wasn't actually in existence,
they use their liens to take the land away from the brother.
Now for תוספות Tosafot it's a very strange because ultimately that's really
unfair. At the end of the day, that way of reading it
is that the brothers would have
inherited two-thirds of this had he never stole it. And because he
stole it, now he's going to do this trick and he's actually
going to get to keep what he stole. So I really don't
know how to explain it. Anyway, three very different ways of explaining
this. רמב"ם Rambam is maybe the easiest to understand. Okay. האומר לבנו
קונם אי אתה נהנה משלי. haomer livno konam ee ata nehene misheli.
If somebody says to a son, I'm making a נדר neder that
you cannot get any benefit from my property. אם מת יירשנו. im
met yirashenu. Okay, if he dies so when the father dies, the
son can still inherit. Because the assumption is you cannot get benefit
when it's mine, but after he dies it's no longer his, it's
the son's, and
therefore it's not a problem.
If he says בחייו ובמותו, bechayav uvimoto, you cannot get any benefit
from this property when I'm alive or even after I'm dead, אם
מת לא יירשנו, im met lo yirashenu, then the son cannot inherit
because then
he would be getting benefit from
property that the נדר neder prevents him from getting benefit from. Now,
אם מת לא יירשנו. im met lo yirashenu.
ויחזיר לבניו ולאחיו. veyachazir lebanav uleachiv.
And therefore the property he's not going to be able to inherit
it and it has to go to,
again, whether the father's brothers and the father's sons or his brothers
and his sons, but it goes to the other
heirs. ואם אין לו, veim ein lo, now let's say he doesn't
have
any... Again, two different ways of reading this. For רמב"ם Rambam it
would mean there are no brothers or heirs. He's the only heir.
So what's going to happen with this property? Or the way רש"י
Rashi or תוספות Tosafot would read it, he can't afford to not
inherit this property. He has no other money. He needs to inherit
this property. So what is he going to
do? לווה ובעלי חוב באים ונפרעים. loveh u'va'alei chov ba'im v'nifra'im. So
this is a lot easier. So let's say this property is worth
$10,000 and he can't afford not to inherit it but the father
made a נדר. neder. So what he does is he borrows
$10,000 and he's not touching the property technically, it's in his possession,
he's not touching it. Once he borrows the $10,000, there are liens
on the property. And then when the borrowers come, he says I
don't have the money or whatever, he doesn't pay them and they
go and they exercise their liens and they collect the property. So
because in that case even though obviously he's benefiting that there was
the property was available to be used to satisfy his debt, nevertheless
because he did not directly derive benefit, he just is using the
cash they gave him and they're exercising their liens, that is understood
to be a way around it that allows that he's not violating
the נדר neder because they're the ones that are directly benefiting from
the property. All right. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, three lines from the top on
ק"ט עמוד א kuf tet amud aleph says רב יוסף: Rav Yosef:
אפילו לארנקי של צדקה. afilu l'arnakei shel tzedaka. If there's nobody to
give it back to and we're going to read this like רמב"ם
Rambam which is the easiest read, there's nobody to give this back
to, no brothers, no sons, or whatever, so רמב"ם Rambam read that
like, okay well you can use it to pay off your creditors,
just get it out of your possession. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef
would say or you could even give it to צדקה. tzedaka. You
know the classic thing as do I owe you $10? I don't
remember. Did I pay you back? Oh just give it to צדקה.
tzedaka. So that idea is already in the גמרא. Gemara. You gotta
get the property out of your hand, says the משנה, Mishna, if
there's no heirs, give it to your creditors or just give it
to צדקה tzedaka says
רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa וצריך שיאמר
זה גזל אבי. v'tzarich she'yomar zeh gezel avi. But for that to
constitute some form of השבה, hashava, some ritual returning of it, then
you have to identify it as such: "This is the property that
I stole from my father." Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמאי נמחליה לנפשיה? amai nimchaleh l'nafsheih? Now says the גמרא, Gemara,
not in this case where the property is still around, but if
the property that was stolen has been destroyed and it's basically just
a debt. So the גמרא Gemara says, why if it's only a
debt is it
important to get it out of your hands? Or why was it
all complicated that if the father died, he couldn't keep the third
that was his? What's the problem says the גמרא? Gemara? Once it's
a debt and the father isn't around and he is an heir,
why doesn't he just say I waive the part that's coming to
me? A third of it should come to me in the case
when he had two
brothers and I waive the part coming to me. Or if he
has no brothers, why does he have to give it to צדקה?
tzedaka? Just say I owe it to myself and I waive the
debt. Now the answer would be because what we're seeing here is
that it's not just a debt. If there's an importance to give
it to צדקה tzedaka or give it to creditors, there's something symbolic
about handing the money over. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to ask. In this case is it just a debt? And
if it's just a debt, then he doesn't have to pay the
part he inherits. He can be מוחל mochel it to himself. And
if he's the only person, he pays nothing. So the משנה Mishna
makes it sound though that it's more than being a debt. It's
actually an act of handing over. But is that really true? Let's
take a look. מי
לא תנן? mi lo tnan? Did we not teach in an earlier
משנה? Mishna? מחלו על הקרן ולא מחלו על החומש. machalu al hakeren
v'lo machalu al hachomesh. That if the person that the money was
stolen from says I מוחל, mochel, like I waive the debt, you
don't have to give me back the קרן, keren, but not the
חומש chomesh and anyway goes on and discusses it. But it's clear
from that משנה Mishna that when a person, the person
from whom it was stolen waives it, we don't say still give
the money back to him. That actually means you're off the hook.
So you see that the key is is there actually a debt
or not. And if the debt has been satisfied even by being
waived, then there is no additional need to do this act of
returning the money. So if that's true, why is this משנה Mishna
so complicated? Father dies,
it's just a debt. Why does he have to go through this
whole thing about giving up his portion to his brothers or finding
a creditor or צדקה? tzedaka? It's just a debt and he's an
heir. So what's the big deal? So let's take a look.
אלמא alma says the גמרא Gemara בר מחילה היא. bar mechila hi.
You see from the משנה Mishna that it's something that מחילה mechila
works and we really focus on it as a debt. So why
is our משנה Mishna demanding this act of handing it over? אמר
רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא רבי יוסי
הגלילי הא רבי עקיבא. ha Rabbi Yossi HaGlili ha Rabbi Akiva. It's
a debate between רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili and רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, whether the early משנה Mishna that
says מחילה Michila works is, we'll see, is רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yose HaGlili who focuses on just the money owed and our משנה
Mishna that clearly needs some act of giving it over is רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who needs this act of handing it over. דתניא,
Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Braisa. ואם לאיש גואל להשיב האשם
אליו. Veim la'ish go'el l'hashiv hasham eilav. If the person has no
redeemer to give the money the thing that was stolen back to,
and the גמרא Gemara will later say that that's talking about a
גר Ger that has no relatives,
then you bring it to the כהן. Kohen. So the ברייתא Braisa
says like this: וכי יש אדם בישראל שאין לו גואלין? Vechi yesh
adam b'Yisrael she'ein lo go'alin? and that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say right here. Is there anybody that doesn't have a
relative that you can give the money back to? אלא בגזל הגר
הכתוב מדבר. Ella b'gezel hager hakatuv m'dabeir. It's talking about you stole
from a גר, Ger, the גר Ger died, there's nobody to give
it back to,
and no relatives, and therefore you give that money, the principal that
you lied about and swore about, you'd give it to the
כהנים. Kohanim. So let's talk about a case. הרי שגזל הגר. Harei
shegazal hager. Let's say somebody stole from this גר. Ger. ונשבע לו,
Venishba lo, and he swore to him. ושמע שמת הגר, Veshama shemeis
hager, and then he heard that the גר Ger died. So now
I'm going to have to bring the money to the כהנים. Kohanim.
והיה מעלה כספו ואשמו לירושלים, Vehaya ma'aleh kaspo ve'ashamo l'Yerushalayim, and was
bringing his money and the קרבן אשם korban asham and was bringing
it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ופגע בו אותו הגר, Upaga bo oto hager,
and then he bumped into the גר, Ger, Mark Twain said, rumors
of my demise have been greatly exaggerated.
So
the גר Ger actually had not died. So now he owes the
money to the גר. Ger. It's a very colorful description of what
happened anyway. וזקפה לו במלוה. Vezakfah lo b'milveh. And the גר Ger
said rather than the guy had the money in his hand, he
had the thousand dollars in his hand, but the גר Ger was
a nice guy and he said you can pay me later, you'll
owe me the
money. ומת, Umeis, and then the גר Ger died. זכה לו במה
שבידו, Zacha lo b'ma sheb'yado, דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי. divrei Rabbi Yose
HaGlili. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili said great, now you're off
the hook. That thousand dollars you can keep. Had the גר Ger
died and you never had, well we'll worry about that
later. But if there was a standard case of the
גר Ger dying and then you came to return the money it
would go to the כהן. Kohen. But in this case because the
גר Ger was
alive and you owed the money to the גר, Ger, so the
כהנים Kohanim are out of the picture. And now when the גר
Ger dies, the principal is that if a גר Ger dies and
he has no children and nobody to inherit his property, whoever first
seizes his property has a right to the property. So you owe
the גר Ger a thousand dollars because you had this little exchange
here,
and then the גר Ger died. So that thousand dollars essentially that
was in your possession that you owed him, now you've seized it
and now it's yours and now you're done. So you see רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili feels that when the debt part of
it goes away, there's no need to do an act of some
type of a ritual act of giving the money over. רבי עקיבא
אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, אין לו תקנה שיציא גזילו מתחת ידו. ein
lo takanah sheyotzi gezeilo miytachas yado.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says sorry that's not going to work. The
fact that you now don't owe money to anybody, you owed it
to the גר Ger and he died so your debt got wiped
away, you're not off the hook until you actually hand over the
thousand dollars. So the גמרא Gemara says that's the debate of רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Is it
just about a debt or is there actually a ritual act of
giving it over? רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili לא שנא לנפשיה לא שנא לאחרים. lo shna
l'nafshei lo shna l'acheirim. And the גמרא Gemara is now going to
read this debate as if they're taking extreme positions. It doesn't matter
if the person you stole
from forgives you the debt, the earlier
משנה, Mishna, the guy who waived the debt, or you are the
heir and in our משנה Mishna and you waived yourself the debt,
you were the heir and therefore you said okay, I owe myself
the money, it's all gone away. Neither of those matters. Basically we
look at it as a debt and if the debt is paid,
however it got paid or waived, you're off the hook. מצי מחיל,
Matzi mochil, you can have it being waived and forgiven and then
you're off the hook. There's no ever an aspect of a ritual
act of giving. ורבי עקיבא, Verabbi Akiva, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
would go to the opposite extreme. לא שנא לאחרים ולא שנא לנפשיה,
Lo shna l'acheirim v'lo shna l'nafshei,
לא מצי מחיל. lo matzi mochil. It doesn't matter whether other people
waived the debt to
you or whether you inherited it and basically you owe yourself the
money.
None of any type of waiving doesn't work. There's always a need
to do a ritual act of giving. All right now the reason
the גמרא Gemara is making these points is because we'll see in
a minute there's a way to read that actually those things do
make a difference and maybe their debate is not as extreme. But
right now the גמרא Gemara is framing the debate as an extreme.
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says it's all about a debt
and if the debt gets erased whether because you were the heir,
because somebody else forgave it, because of the case of the גר,
Ger, then you're off the hook. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
it's all about a ritual act of giving. I don't care how
the debt got erased, you still have to do the act. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this and therefore that explains
it. The earlier משנה Mishna that spoke about מחילה mechila was רבי
יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, our משנה Mishna that says that if
the father dies, there still has to be some ritual act of
giving, that's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: לא מצא מהא ורבי עקיבא לא תנא דאפילו לא מצא
מחל. lo matza m'ha v'Rabbi Akiva lo tana d'afillu lo matza m'chal.
ולרבי יוסי הוא הדין דאפילו לא זקפו במלוה. v'l'Rabbi Yose hu hadin
d'afillu lo zakfo b'milveh. And according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, really
says the גמרא, Gemara, you didn't need the case of the גר
ger bumping into the גר ger and the גר ger saying 'you
know what, it'll be a loan'.
Why? Because even if the גר ger didn't say that, in your
mind, you thought the גר ger had died and you were bringing
the money to the כהנים. Kohanim. But the reality was that the
גר ger was alive. So the reality was that you owed the
גר ger the money, and then the גר ger died, okay, and
therefore now you, now the debt is erased. Anybody who owes money
to a גר, ger, once the גר ger dies, the debt is
erased. Okay, so in רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, you really
didn't need the scenario of bumping into the גר. ger. Okay, now
we'll have to talk about what is the case that the money
actually goes to the כהנים. Kohanim. Doesn't it sound like always it
would get erased? Okay, so we'll see about that later, but the
point the גמרא Gemara is making is that for רבי יוסי הגלילי,
Rabbi Yose HaGlili, if it's all about a debt, then you swore
to the גר, ger, you owe the גר ger the money, the
גר ger dies, the debt gets erased, because that's what happens when
a גר ger dies, his, you know,
money owed to him, if there's no heirs or whatever, the debt
just gets erased, and therefore you're off the hook. Okay, so ולרבי
יוסי הגלילי הוא הדין אפילו לא זקפו במלוה, u'l'Rabbi Yose HaGlili hu
hadin afillu lo zakfo b'milveh, even if you didn't have that encounter
where the גר ger said, 'it'll be like you owe me the
money, you'll just owe it to me'. והא דקתני זקפו במלוה, v'ha
d'katani zakfo b'milveh, so why did it give that scenario? להודיעך כוחו
דרבי עקיבא דאפילו זקפנוהו במלוה אין לו תקנה שיצא גזילו מתחת ידו.
l'hodi'acha kocho d'Rabbi Akiva d'afillu zakfannuhu b'milveh ein lo takana sheyeitzei gezeilo
mitachat yado. You might have thought that even though רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva requires a ritual giving, if the גר ger says, 'you know
what, you'll owe me the money', maybe that would have been like
you gave him the money and he lent it back to you.
Sometimes we imagine that. Let it be, you know, like you'll owe
me the money, you'll pay it to me later. So maybe for
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that would have counted as a ritual act
of giving, and it says no. Okay, so what is the גמרא
Gemara saying now? We have an earlier משנה Mishna that says that
מחילה mechila works. We have our משנה Mishna that if you're an
heir, tough luck, you still have to give it. It seems like
there's a debate here about whether to think of גזל הגר gezel
hager and the obligation just in terms of money owed or a
ritual act of giving. The גמרא Gemara says that's a debate of
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says it's just a debt, that was
the earlier משנה, Mishna, מחילה mechila works. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
there's a ritual act of giving, that's our משנה, Mishna, so if
you're the only heir, you have to find a way to get
it out of your possession. The case of the גר ger is
the case of it doesn't really matter whether there was, it turned
into a loan or didn't turn into a loan. At the end
of the day, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili would always say,
you know, you're exempt because it's just a debt and once the
גר ger dies, the debt is erased. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
would say you're always חייב, chayav, even if it was a loan,
you didn't actually give it, and therefore you still have to go
ahead and give the money after the גר ger dies. Okay, so
that's read number one, that they take extreme positions. מתיב
לה רב ששת. matkiv lah Rav Sheshet. רב ששת Rav Sheshet challenged
this reading of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אי
הכי לרבי יוסי הגלילי לשמעינן לנפשיה וכל שכן
לאחרים.
i hachi l'Rabbi Yose HaGlili lishmi'inan l'nafsheih
v'chol shekein l'acherim.
If that's true, that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says that
it's all about the debt, why is the one משנה Mishna that
we have of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili when the person
you stole it from forgives you? That could be seen maybe, since
you're dealing with the person you stole it from and he says
'I forgive you', that's a case that maybe could be thought of
as if you gave him the money. It's a much bigger חידוש
chiddush to say that even when you're the heir and there is
nobody external to forgive you, that even in that case, all it
is is a debt and you don't have to worry about it.
So if רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili thought מחילה mechila worked
in all cases, why does he only give us the earlier משנה
Mishna about the נגזל nigzal doing מחילה? mechila? He should have said
his הלכה halacha in our משנה, Mishna, that there was no other
party and nevertheless it's just a debt and you're exempt. Okay, ולרבי
יוסי הגלילי לשמעינן לנפשיה, u'l'Rabbi Yose HaGlili lishmi'inan l'nafsheih, give us the
case when you're forgiving yourself the debt, our משנה, Mishna, וכל שכן
לאחרים, v'chol shekein l'acherim, and certainly in the case where the נגזל
nigzal forgives it, that would certainly work. And you could say the
same for רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, remember we
said our משנה Mishna that said when you were the heir, you
had to do some ritual act of giving, that was רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that requires a ritual act. But why does he only
say the case where you're the only party? ולרבי עקיבא לשמעינן לאחרים
דלא מהני מחילה. u'l'Rabbi Akiva lishmi'inan l'acherim d'lo mahani mechila.
He should have told us that even if the נגזל nigzal says
it's forgiven, even then you still have to give it to him.
That's a huge חידוש, chiddush, the נגזל nigzal actively forgives you and
you still have to give it to him. וכל שכן לנפשיה, v'chol
shekein l'nafsheih, certainly if like you're the only party, like in our
משנה Mishna where you're the only heir. So I get how you
could explain it's an extreme debate, but it's funny that our משניות
Mishnayot which you're lining up are taking the least strong positions for
each of those positions. אלא, Ela, so right therefore it makes much
more sense to say that the debate is much smaller than you
framed it. אמר אביי Amar Abaye says, הא והא רבי יוסי הגלילי.
Ha V'ha Rabbi Yossi HaGlili. They're both רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yossi
HaGlili, both the משנה Mishna that מחילה Mechila works, the earlier משנה
Mishna and our משנה Mishna that, when you're the only heir, you
still have to give it. כי קאמר רבי יוסי הגלילי דמצי מחיל
לאחרים, אבל לנפשיה לא מצי מחיל. Ki Ka'amar Rabbi Yossi HaGlili Dematzi
Machil Le'acherim, Aval L'nafshei Lo Matzi Machil.
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili says, look, I do agree that
there has to be some type of
a giving back. But if you try to give back and the
נגזל Nigzal says I forgive you, that counts as a giving back.
Okay, so that's enough if it's forgiven through somebody else, or if
the גר Ger says it's a loan and then the גר Ger
dies, that counts as if he forgave it you. There's an exchange
with the other person around this around what you owe them. That
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili would say is okay. But in
our case of the
where you're the sole heir, so in that case you know there's
no act that can be considered some act of returning. It's just
okay there's nobody you owe money to. And in that case even
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili is not satisfied. So that's much
easier. First of all it has both משניות Mishnayot going according to
the same position. And it says you know even רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yossi HaGlili fundamentally admits there has to be some type of
an act with the person you stole it from. And therefore in
our משנה Mishna you got a problem. You're the only person, you
gotta find some way to you're the only heir, you gotta find
some way to give this thing away. But in the other cases
of the גר Ger and of the and of the נגזל, Nigzal,
when they forgave it to you or when the גר Ger made
it a loan and then he died, that's like an act as
if you gave it back. Okay, so that's his read.
אלא אבל לנפשיה לא מצי. אלא הא מאי זכה הלה במה שבידו
משום דזקפיה עליה במלוה. Ela Aval L'nafshei Lo Matzi. Ela Ha Mai
Zachah Halei Bema Shebeyado? Mishum Dezakfeih Aleih Bemilveh. And therefore why in
the case of the גר Ger did that work? Because that case
since the גר Ger converted it into a into a loan, right,
it's not just the debt that you had—I don't know if I
said this clearly enough before—the debt you had from stealing from him.
That's a debt to pay what you stole. The גר Ger then
said let's convert it to a loan. It's as if you paid
it to me and I now lent you the money back. So
in that type of a case that counts as if it was
returned. The same way when the נגזל Nigzal forgives it, it's as
if it was returned. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is not happy with
that. He always needs an act of returning. But רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yossi HaGlili says I will consider these types of things, מחילה,
Mechila, turning it into converting it to a loan as a type
of a giving, but not our משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna you're
the only party and therefore you still need to get it out
of your possession. Okay, רבא
אמר,
Rava
Amar,
רבא Rava takes a similar approach except says it that does it
through רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. הא והא רבי עקיבא. Ha V'ha Rabbi
Akiva. Both of the משניות Mishnayot are רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. כי
קאמר רבי עקיבא דלא מצי מחיל לנפשיה, אבל לאחרים מצי מחיל. Ki
Ka'amar Rabbi Akiva D'lo Matzi Machil L'nafshei, Aval Le'acherim Matzi Machil. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was only debating with רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi
HaGlili that you had to get it out of your possession in
the case of the גר. Ger. Because the גר Ger was never
מוחל. Mochel. The גר Ger just died. So in that case he
says that's you know that doesn't count as an act of returning.
But when a third part when the נגזל Nigzal actively forgives you,
that for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does count like an act of
returning. Okay, so the same idea. In the משנה, Mishna, the reason
it worked by מחילה, Mechila, the earlier משנה, Mishna, is that counts
as an act of forgiving. In our case where you're the only
person, obviously I mean the משנה Mishna where it was forgiven that
counts as an act of returning. In our משנה Mishna where you're
the heir, there's no act of returning, you're stuck, you gotta go
ahead and give it. Okay, and how do you understand the debate
of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili and רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva?
According to one approach, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili you know
says that
that even the case of a גר Ger is like a third
party forgiving, is like the earlier משנה. Mishna. And and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva would say even when a third party forgives, I don't
care, you still have to return it. That was the position of
רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. Or different, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili
is you know you know is always okay when the debt gets
erased. But רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say okay with it when
a third party does it, you know the other person, but not
when it happens automatically. And my issue is that I think the
case of the גר Ger is a case that it happens automatically.
כי קאמר רבי עקיבא דלא מצי מחיל לנפשיה, אבל לאחרים מצי מחיל.
Ki Ka'amar Rabbi Akiva D'lo Matzi Machil L'nafshei, Aval Le'acherim Matzi Machil.
So
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is the one that says I'm okay when
somebody else does it, I'm not okay when it happens by itself.
It's just that I consider the גר Ger case to be a
case that it happens by itself. מכלל דרבי יוסי הגלילי סבר אפילו
לנפשיה נמי מצי מחיל. Michlal DeRabbi Yossi HaGlili Savar Afilu L'nafshei Nami
Matzi Machil.
So according to this read רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili would
say you know our משנה Mishna would just be רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili would say that even if
you're the only... Only party, even if it gets erased automatically, you're
good. Alright, so again, three multiple different ways of reading it. The
first way is it's an extreme debate. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGelili considers it to be just a debt and when that gets
erased, you're fine. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva always requires that it be
returned, doesn't matter, a third party, yourself, anything. That's the extreme position.
Next position is רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili says that everybody
agrees there needs to be some act of returning. Okay, it's just
that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili is willing to consider the
מחילה mechila of the נגזל nigzal or the death of the גר
ger to be an act of returning because it's another party and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is not. Third possibility: רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yose HaGelili says it's just a debt and you don't need any
act of returning at all and you're done and that's רבי יוסי
הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGelili. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you need an
act of returning. The case of מחילה mechila counts as an act
of returning, the case of the גר ger does not count as
an act of returning. Okay, hope you got all that. There'll be
a test on that tomorrow.
Anyway, אלא, ella, now the גמרא Gemara wants to ask this question.
If you say that when the גר ger died naturally even without
converting it to a debt, since it's that even when the גר
ger to even when the to converting it to a loan, excuse
me, that when the גר ger dies naturally you're exempt, that we
only look at this through the lens of pure debt. Okay, this
גזל, gezel, this type of גזל gezel and a שבועה shevuah never
need an act of returning. It's just a question of debt. If
the debt is erased, you're off the hook. If that's true, then
in the case of a גר ger even if he didn't convert
it to a loan, once he dies, you're free from your debt
to him. So if that's true, when do you ever give the
money to the כהנים? kohanim? אלא גזל הגר דקאמר רחמנא נתינה לכהנים
היכי משכחת לה? ella gezel hager de'kamar rachmana nesina lekohanim heichi mashkachas
la? What would be the case? Because every time the גר ger
dies, the loans that are owed to him are erased. And if
according to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili it's only a debt,
then you're done. אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, הכא במאי
עסקינן כשגזל את הגר ונשבע לו ומת הגר והודה לאחר מיתה. hacha
bemai askinan keshegezal es hager venishba lo u-meis hager vehoda l'achar misa.
Ah,
you're right. The only case you would have it is you stole
from the גר, ger, you swore, the גר ger first died, and
then you admitted to what you did. In that case, the debt
comes into existence after the גר ger is dead. And since the
גר ger isn't around, the debt comes into existence to the כהנים.
kohanim. But if you admitted when the גר ger was alive and
the debt came into existence to the גר, ger, then once the
גר ger died, you're off the hook because according to this approach
in רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGelili, it's only ever a debt,
there is never needs an act of giving, and the debt got
erased when the גר ger died. But again, if you were הודה
לאחר מיתה, hode l'achar misa, if you admitted afterwards, דבעידנא דהודה קננהו
השם ונתנהו לכהנים, d'be'idna de'hode kano Hashem unesano l'kohanim,
that then there was never a debt to the גר, ger, when
you admitted it was automatically owed to השם Hashem and therefore essentially
owed to the כהנים. kohanim. Okay, בעי רבינא. ba'ei Ravina. Now רבינא
Ravina asks. So we're finally done with that, but that was a
really getting to the heart of our משנה, mishnah, getting to the
heart of the nature of the obligation of swearing and having to
return. Do we look at this as just a debt or do
we also look at it as something that requires a ritual act
of giving? Our משנה mishnah certainly makes it sound like you need
a ritual act of giving. And then the גמרא Gemara wanted to
figure out how does this debate of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGelili and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, how does that play out? Are
there extreme positions? Are there more narrow positions of when a third
party is involved it's like you gave it? And we raised a
whole range of possibilities. Now we're going on to a different point
about stealing from the גר. ger. בעי רבינא גזל גיורת מהו? ba'ei
Ravina gezel giyores mahu? If you stole from a female גיורת giyores
and she died and she has no heirs, does that also go
to the כהנים? kohanim? Does the פסוק pasuk say איש, ish, אמר
רחמנא אם אין לאיש גואל, amar rachmana im ein l'ish go'el,
the man has no redeemers? ולא אשה, ve'lo isha, not a woman.
Oh, and it's like a גזירת הכתוב, gzeiras hakasuv, this idea that
it goes to כהנים kohanim is only by a male גר. ger.
או דילמא אורחא דקרא הוא, o dilma orchi de'kra hu, that's just
an or do you say that's just a normal way the פסוק
pasuk talks? It doesn't specifically meant to exclude women. אמר ליה רב
אהרן, Amar lei Rav Aaron, interesting, רב אהרן Rav Aaron is a
very rare name. אמר ליה רב אהרן לרבינא תא שמע Amar lei
Rav Aaron l'Ravina tashma come hear דתניא, de-tanya, איש אין לי אלא
איש. ish ein li ella ish. We got a ברייתא. braisa. The
ברייתא braisa says you stole from a man and the man has
no redeemers, which means he's a גר. ger. I only know a
man. אשה מנין? isha minayin? How do I know a woman? כשהוא
אומר keshehu omer when the פסוק pasuk says המושב, hamushav, האשם המושב
לכהן, ha'asham hamushav lakohain,
that is returned, which is an extra word, הרי כאן שנים, harei
kan shnayim, it's telling you that even it gets returned even to
another type of a person. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר איש? im
kein ma talmud lomar ish? So then why does it say איש?
ish? איש אתה צריך לחזור אחריו אם יש לו גואל אם לאו
קטן אי אתה צריך לחזור אחריו בידוע שאין לו גואלים, ish ata
tzarich lachzor acharav im yesh lo go'el im lav katan iy ata
tzarich lachzor acharav biydu'a she'ein lo go'alim,
because it says the man has no redeemers meaning no relatives, no
heirs, so that's only true once he's a man, you have to
investigate. gate whether he has any heirs because he might have fathered
a child. But if somebody is a minor, then you automatically
you wouldn't have to say אין לאיש גואל ein la-ish goel automatically
you would know again if he were a גר ger that he
would have no relatives who could inherit from him and therefore because
this teaches you the principle that for a minor we are not
concerned that he might have fathered children again a minor under thirteen
and you do not have to investigate and it would immediately go
to the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, we will stop here.